Hello everyone and welcome to
English Mod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine
and today we're talking
about something that is well
not so fun when it happens.
That's right today
we're going to talk about
those situations where people
are trying to take advantage of us.
Alright they're lying to us
so they can take our money.
Let's take a listen to
today's dialogue and
when we come back in
a moment we'll be talking
about some of these words and
phrases that you're about to hear.
I got an urgent email from Tom.
He says he's in London
and got robbed and
needs us to wire him
some money for his hotel.
What?
That sounds really dodgy to me.
No way, Tom is an honest
person, he wouldn't lie to me.
No I mean it seems like someone may have
hacked his email account and sent that out.
I mean think about it.
Why would he email
you instead of calling you?
Do you really think someone is trying
to scam people into sending money?
For sure.
There's so many con artists
out there you never really know.
Alright we're back so let's take a look at
some language on language take away.
Language take away.
In language take
away Marco one of the
first things we hear is that I
got an urgent email from Tom.
That's right so this is an
adjective something that is urgent.
It's urgent that means it needs
to be looked at immediately.
It's very important.
That's right.
You can have an urgent
email that means it's
very important email or something
as a situation can be urgent.
Yeah like an emergency,
so urgent care we
talk about at the hospital
it's something that
needs to be looked at by a
doctor immediately, urgently.
That's right, urgently
that would be the adverb.
Now we go on to say
that the email is urgent
because it's from Tom and the email said
that he is in London and he got robbed.
Alright he got robbed.
So to rob is the verb R O B but here
it's important to look at the verb got.
This means that
whatever's happening it
happened to him, to the
friend, by someone else.
That's right.
So someone robbed him.
Alright he got robbed.
That means someone took his money right?
That's right.
But the verb would be to get and
robbed would be an adjective ending ED.
But we also have the
verb to rob and if you
rob someone that means that
you are stealing his or her money.
Yeah if I rob Marco it means I
take Marco's money from him.
But if I got robbed by Marco
it means he took my money.
That's right.
So remember if you
use the verb to rob by
itself that means that
you are doing the action
or someone is stealing
from another person.
But if you get robbed
or a person got robbed
that means he or her got
money taken from him.
Now the friend got robbed,
someone took his money
and we've been asked
to wire him some money.
Okay to wire money.
That's right to wire money and
this basically means to send money.
It's a very old way or
form of sending money.
Basically you're sending
money electronically.
You don't actually buy an envelope and put
some money in it and send it in the mail.
You go to a bank or Western Union
and you transfer the money electronically.
That's right.
So to send an electronic transfer of money
we usually say you wire someone some money.
Yeah I'll wire it to you.
That's right.
Alright now continuing on
the main topic about today's
lesson is about people
trying to scam other people.
Right here the verb
to scam means to lie or
to be dishonest with
someone so that you can
take their money or to
take advantage of them.
That's right.
So to scam means to
take advantage of someone
to lie to someone but
you also have a scam
a noun which is a situation where
people are trying to take your money.
So a very famous scam
might be people in a
big city like Paris
saying oh I'm a tourist.
I'm lost can you help
me can you give me some
money to go to the train station
and really these people they're not lost.
They just want you to give them money.
That's right.
So this is called a scam and what they're
doing is they are trying to scam you.
That's right and so we actually
have a word for these type of people.
We say they are a con
artist they are coning you.
A con artist okay so we
know what an artist is.
An artist is a person
who maybe paints pictures
or makes something creative but a
con is someone who breaks the law.
So a con artist is someone
who creatively breaks the law.
That's right.
So these are basically
thieves or people who
take advantage of other
people or steal from
other people in a very
creative way so there
are situations where they may sell something
that doesn't even really belong to them.
That's right.
So the thing to
remember here with a con
artist is that there's
almost always a story.
You know you have
to they give you this
story they make you
believe them and then you
give them money or
you you give them some
help that they don't deserve and
that that way they take it away from you.
That's right.
All right so we've taken a look at a lot of
language here let's take a break listen to
the dialogue again and
we'll be back in a bit.
I got an urgent email from
Tom he says he's in London got
robbed and needs us to wire
him some money for his hotel.
What?
That sounds really dodgy to me.
No way Tom is an honest
person he wouldn't lie to me.
No I mean it seems like someone may have
hacked his email account and sent that out.
I mean think about it.
Why would he email
you instead of calling you?
Do you really think someone is trying
to scam people into sending money?
For sure there's so many con artists
out there you never really know.
We're back let's take a look at
4 key phrases on fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
So we've got two friends
who are talking one
friend says that they
got an urgent email
from Tom and the other says
wow that sounds really dodgy to me.
That's right so if something sounds dodgy
or something is dodgy it means it doesn't
really sound believable
or correct or legal.
That's right so maybe I can't trust it.
I think you can say it about a situation
so this robbery it sounds quite dodgy.
We can also say it about food right?
It doesn't really look safe.
Maybe I'll be sick if I eat it
so it's quite dodgy looking.
Or even a person can
look dodgy so maybe
that person is not really
someone you want to trust.
A con artist doesn't always look dodgy but
if a person looks dodgy and they ask you
for money probably
shouldn't give it any money.
Exactly.
That's dodgy.
The person answers by saying no way Tom
is an honest person, he wouldn't lie to me.
He's not dodgy.
No way.
Right.
Now this is a really popular thing to say
and it means basically that's not possible.
I don't agree with you.
I disagree.
And it's pretty forceful actually
you're expressing your opinion.
So if I say the Chicago White Sox
are the best baseball team in the world.
No way.
No you're wrong.
The Yankees are the best.
We could go back and forth.
No way.
Right exactly.
Basically you're disagreeing.
That's right.
Now the situation
evolves around the fact that
someone may have hacked Tom's
email account and send out that email.
All right.
So the phrase here would be to
hack an account or to hack a website.
It's important to remember that
the verb to hack is pretty recent.
We talk mostly about computers and
the internet when we talk about hacking.
Right.
And it means to gain access to go into
some buddy's account without permission.
Right.
So maybe illegally or like
you said without permission.
So if your email account
gets hacked, someone
else accessed it without
your permission or illegally.
So when someone has access
to your account, they hack it.
Usually they send out
an email with your name.
So your friends think
it's you but really it's
someone who is maybe a con artist
or someone who's not trustworthy.
That's right.
That's exactly right.
So that's the word to
hack or maybe the noun,
the person that hacks
is called a hacker.
Now moving on to our last phrase.
When we agree with someone forcefully
like we said no way was to disagree.
When we do agree we say for sure.
That's right.
This is basically the opposite.
In this situation we
were thinking well, do
you really think someone
is trying to hack his account?
The answer was for sure.
That means definitely, absolutely.
That's right.
So for sure.
It's another way of
agreeing, strongly agreeing
with someone or with
what someone said.
For sure.
All right.
So that's all we have for today.
Listen to the dialogue one last
time, I got an urgent email from Tom.
He says he's in London
and got robbed and
needs us to wire him
some money for his hotel.
What?
That sounds really dodgy to me.
No way.
Tom is an honest person.
He wouldn't lie to me.
No.
I mean it seems like someone may have
hacked his email account and sent that out.
I mean think about it.
Why would he email
you instead of calling you?
Do you really think someone is trying
to scam people into sending money?
For sure.
There's so many con artists
out there, you never really know.
All right.
We're back.
So talking about scams
and con artists in China,
there is actually a very, very,
very famous scam involving tea.
That's right.
And this is something
that you might experience
in Beijing or Shanghai
or any big city.
I hope you don't.
But basically, as a
tourist, you're traveling
around, you go to a
major tourist site like
Tiananmen or the
people square in Shanghai.
And some other tourists,
some Chinese tourists,
they come to you
and they say, "Hello.
Where are you from?
Are you traveling here?
We're traveling too.
" And then after about
half an hour, maybe one
hour of talking, they say, "Hey, we were
thinking about going to have some tea.
There's a tea festival.
Would you like to come with us?
" Right.
So when you drink some
tea and you chat and you
think, "Wow, I've made
some nice new friends.
These people are very nice.
" And then you get the bill.
Right.
And it's like $200 US dollars,
which is pretty crazy for tea.
Exactly.
It's a scam.
These people are con artists.
They build trust.
They make you trust them.
They make you think,
"Wow, I have nice new friends.
" And then they
steal your money.
They steal your money.
That's right.
It's a very popular scam in China.
And basically, if you do
come here, just be aware of it.
It's usually young people.
They say they're university students
or they say they are from another city.
And like you say, they build trust.
They invite you to have tea
and you think, "Well, why not?
" You know, to learn
more about the culture, to
learn more about the
country you're visiting.
And they turn out to try to scam you.
That's right.
And another popular one is the artists.
I'm a local artist.
I would like to show you my newest work.
And then they take you and the work is
very expensive and they make you buy it.
So it's be be aware.
I think what you said is true, Marco, that,
you know, you just have to be careful.
You have to have to recognize that
not everyone wants to be your friend.
Exactly.
So be careful when you're traveling.
And I'm sure it happens
in many other countries.
Maybe you have
some stories that you've
experienced or maybe
some local types of
scams that you may
know about in your country.
That's right.
Let us know.
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
Try and use those new
words, con artist and scam.
We'll be around answering your questions.
Let us know.
EnglishPod.com.
We'll see you there.
Bye.